Guide to the School of Hotel Administration Director's records, 1922-1981.
School of Hotel Administration Director's records, 1922-1981.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
School of Hotel Administration Director's records, 1922-1981.
28-1-1803
Cornell University. School of Hotel Administration. Director.
10.1 cubic ft.
Correspondence, files, albums, records, reports, meeting minutes, plaques.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Records of the Director's Office and of Howard B. Meek include registration reports as well as school budgets, minutes of faculty and staff meetings, and reports.
ORGANIZATIONAL HISTORY
Directors and deans represented include Howard B. Meek, Robert A. Beck, and John J. Clark.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Records of the Director's Office include correspondence files; biographical files; and subject files, including files of the Courtney Memorial Fund. Records of Howard B. Meek include registration reports, with letters to Meek; correspondence; items relating to a Hotel School European tour; and plaques and awards given to Meek. Also, school budgets, 1954-1978; minutes of faculty and staff meetings, 1935-1981; report of the Education Committee of the American Hotel Association, 1944; and minutes of Deans' Council meetings, 1968-1970.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Cornell University.; Beck, Robert Alfred, 1920-; Clark, John J.; Meek, Howard B., 1893-
Subjects:
Hotel management--Study and teaching.; Hotel management schools--New York (State)--Ithaca.
Places:
Europe--Description and travel.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
SERIES LIST
Series I. History
Boxes 1-2, 12
Subseries I. Chronological files
Subseries II. Biographical files
Subseries III. Subject file
Subseries IV. Courtney Memorial Fund
Subseries V. Registration Reports
Series II. Howard B. Meek files
Boxes 1, 4-11
Subseries I. Administrative Records
-Registration reports
-Correspondence
-Miscellaneous
Subseries II. European tour
Subseries III. Commemorative Items
-Plaques and awards
-Loose material
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. History
  - Subseries I. Chronological files
    - Correspondence, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Correspondence, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Correspondence, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Correspondence, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Correspondence, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Correspondence, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Correspondence, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Correspondence, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Correspondence, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Correspondence, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Correspondence, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Correspondence, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Correspondence, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Correspondence, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Correspondence, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Correspondence, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Correspondence, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Correspondence, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Correspondence, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Correspondence, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Correspondence, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Correspondence, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Chronological list of important events, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Chef's course, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - NCR posting machine (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Tourism (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Subseries II. Biographical files (list of folder contents in front of each file)
    - Boomer, Lucius M. (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Callis, Harold B. (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Day, Edmund E. (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Eppley, Eugene C. (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Gibson, A.W. and Student War Service Committee (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Green, Thomas D. (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Hamilton, W.I. (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Herndon, James B. (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Hoie, John McF., 1913-1958 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - Kief, Raymond J. (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - McHatton, George (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - McKowne, Frank A., 1923-1944 (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - Meek, Howard B. (Box 1, Folder 53)
    - Needham, William R. (Box 1, Folder 54)
    - Owen, Emerson (Box 1, Folder 55)
    - Pinco, Charles N. (Box 1, Folder 56)
    - Randolph, Frank H. (Box 1, Folder 57)
    - Recknagel, Helen J. (Box 1, Folder 58)
    - Rose, Flora (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Shircliff, Arnold (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Statler, Alice and Ellsworth M., 1923-1962 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Toth, Lewis (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Tschirky, Oscar, Leo, and Robert (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Van Rensselaer, Martha (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Vehling, Joseph D. (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Windsor, Andrew L. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Subseries III. Subject file
    - Accelerated program (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Army - Reg. QM students (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Budget folder (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - CPA (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Cornell Society of Hotelmen (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Subseries IV. Courtney Memorial Fund
    - Courtney memorial fund (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - CICSF, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - "Impact of Hotel School Alumni Felt throughout the World," by Frank Ready (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Cornell Alumni Corporation (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Alumni Trustee nominations (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Bills and vouchers (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Correspondence course, 1920-1940's (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Good housekeeping (Lewis course) (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Home Economics miscellany (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Hospital administration course explorations, 1927-1947 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Menu planning course (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Insurance course (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - National hotel exposition trips, 1924-1941 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Navy program (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Naval ROTC (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - ROTC (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Navy and marine possibilities (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Old faculty (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Olympics (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Other hotel schools, philosophy on (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Placement, 1927-1951 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Real estate course (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Research (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - First explanatory conference on research in fields related to the operation of hotels, July 9, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - First explanatory conference on research in fields related to the operation of hotels, July 9, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Reports and recommendations, November 17, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Research (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Subseries V. Registration Reports
    - Reports on Student Registration submitted to the Dean, 1938-1970 (Box 12, Folder 1-38)
- Series II. Howard B. Meek files
  - Subseries I. Administrative Records
    - Registration reports
      - Letter to H.B. Meek, October 1940 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - Letter to H.B. Meek, February 1941 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Letter to H.B. Meek, October 1941 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Letter to H.B. Meek, February 1942 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - Letter to H.B. Meek, September 1942 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Letter to H.B. Meek, February 1943 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Letter to H.B. Meek, July 1943 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Letter to H.B. Meek, November 1943 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Letter to H.B. Meek, Spring 1944 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Letter to H.B. Meek, July 1944 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Letter to H.B. Meek, November 1944 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Letter to H.B. Meek, March 1949 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Estimated registration, February 1940 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - Expected registration, February 1940 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - Expected registration, September 1941 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - Registration, September 1940 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      - Registration, February 1941 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      - Registration, September 1941 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      - Registration, February 1942 (Box 1, Folder 19)
      - Registration Report, 1940 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - Registration Report, 1941 (Box 4, Folder 2)
      - Registration Report, 1941 (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - Registration Report, 1942 (Box 4, Folder 4)
      - Registration Report, 1942 (Box 4, Folder 5)
      - Registration Report, 1943 (Box 4, Folder 6)
      - Registration Report, 1943 (Box 4, Folder 7)
      - Registration Report, 1943 (Box 4, Folder 8)
      - Registration Report, 1944 (Box 4, Folder 9)
      - Registration Report, 1944 (Box 4, Folder 10)
      - Registration Report, 1944 (Box 4, Folder 11)
      - Registration Report, 1949 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence
      - A-C, 1948-1951 (Box 4, Folder 13)
      - "To Buildings and Grounds", 1948-1950 (Box 4, Folder 14)
      - "To Day", 1942-1950 (Box 4, Folder 15)
      - "To Holabird and Root and Burgee", 1941-1950 (Box 4, Folder 16)
      - D-O, February 1942 (Box 4, Folder 17)
      - "To Parke", February 1942 (Box 4, Folder 18)
      - P-Z, February 1942 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Miscellaneous
      - Miscellaneous, February 1942 (Box 4, Folder 20)
      - Miscellaneous, 1947-1949 (Box 4, Folder 21)
      - Report No. V, 1949 (Box 4, Folder 22)
      - Statler Hotel Sound Equipment, 1948 (Box 4, Folder 23)
      - Sample Hotel School Exam Questions, 1937 (Box 4, Folder 24)
      - Cornerstone ceremonies (Box 5, Folder 1)
      - Purchasing department (Box 5, Folder 2)
      - Sayles, Charles I. (Box 5, Folder 3)
      - Dedication (Box 5, Folder 4)
      - Faculty Club (Box 5, Folder 5)
      - Bamberth, Hugo (Box 5, Folder 6)
      - Meek retirement (Box 5, Folder 7)
      - OPA (Office of Price Administration) and Palmer, Archie M. (Box 5, Folder 8)
      - OPA (Box 5, Folder 9-10)
      - Minimum Wage Board, New York State Department of Labor (Box 5, Folder 11)
      - Kittamat Hotel survey (Box 5, Folder 12)
      - Thayer Hotel (Box 5, Folder 13)
      - Statler Foundation (Box 5, Folder 14)
      - Buying retirement on the loss of state status (Box 6, Folder 12)
      - Sales course (Box 6, Folder 13)
      - Scholarships (Box 6, Folder 14)
      - Secretarial science (Box 6, Folder 15)
      - National Executive Housekeepers Association (Summer School) (Box 6, Folder 16)
      - Teacher Training for Chefs (Box 6, Folder 17)
      - Veterans Administration, 1946-1951 (Box 6, Folder 18)
      - Wines course (Box 6, Folder 19)
      - Binder with plates from the Edgewater Beach Salad Book by Arnold Shircliffe, presented to the Meeks (Box 7)
  - Subseries II. European tour
    - Hotel tour participants, 1955 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Participants and prospects, correspondence re European hotel and restaurant executives tour, 1953 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Pictures and questionnaires, 1955 (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Miscellany, 1955 (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Prospects (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Meek correspondence concerning tours, 1954-1956 (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Flyers, maps, etc. (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - "Old" (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Itineraries, etc. (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Promotion (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Promotion - early (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Vouchers, 1958 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Europe memoirs, 1953 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Subseries III. Commemorative Items
    - Plaques and awards
      - Hotel Ezra Cornell - appreciation plaque (Box 6, Folder 7)
      - Scroll signed by members of the New York Branch of the Cornell Society of Hotel Men, in appreciation of Meek's 10th Anniversary of starting the Hotel Course, April 1932 (Box 11)
      - Certificate signed by the Governor of Nebraska, appointing him Admiral in the Navy of Nebraska, 1954 (Box 11)
      - Pacific Air Force plaque for Outstanding Service Open Mess Training Course at the Imperial Hotel - Tokyo, Japan, 1959 (Box 7)
      - Hotel Association of Washington, D.C. - plaque for outstanding service, April 3, 1961 (Box 6, Folder 8)
      - "The Southern Exposition for Hotels, Motels and Restaurants" - Appreciation plaque, April 4, 1961 (Box 7)
      - Texas Hotel and Motel Association, Distinguished Service Award, May 5, 1964 (Box 6, Folder 9)
      - New York State Hotel Association, honorary life membership card (Box 6, Folder 10)
      - Honorary citizen of Texas, May 25, 1961 (Box 6, Folder 11)
      - "The Growth of an Idea," scrapbook documenting the first 25 years of the Hotel School (Box 6, Folder 20)
      - "Testimonial Dinner in Honor of Dean Howard Bagnall Meek," scrapbook, January 9, 1961 (Box 6, Folder 21)
      - "Meekbake," The New England Chapter of the Cornell Society of Hotelmen, scrapbook, March 10, 1961 (Box 6, Folder 22)
      - "Testimonial Dinner in Honor of Dean Howard B. Meek," scrapbook, March 16, 1961 (Box 6, Folder 23)
      - "Professor Howard Bagnall Meek," testimonial dinner, Mayflower Hotel (album), April 3, 1961 (Box 11)
      - Certificate of appreciation from Cornell Society of Hotelmen, 1969 (Box 11)
      - "A Pictorial Commemorative of the visit of Professor H.B. Meek and the Graduating Class of the Hotel Administration of Cornell University to the Greenbriar..." (photograph album), June 13-15, 1937 (Box 7)
    - Loose material
      - Loose material from testimonial dinner album, including photographs, 1961 (Box 7, Folder 1)
      - H.B. Meek miscellany (Box 7, Folder 2)
      - Trip to South America, 1950-1951 (Box 7, Folder 3)
      - Miscellaneous Cornell University material (Box 7, Folder 4-5)
      - Hotel management clippings, Bureau of Good Ideas (Box 7, Folder 6)
      - Menus, etc., not used (Box 7, Folder 7)
      - European trip miscellany (Box 7, Folder 8-9)
      - Hotel accounting, slide preparation (Box 7, Folder 10)
      - "Federal Reserve Policy" paper by Meek, 1929 (Box 7, Folder 11)
      - Certificate in Spanish given to Meek (1951); Signed photo (1932); Slide of Mr. and Mrs. Meek (Box 7, Folder 12)
      - School Budgets, 1954-1978 (Box 8)
      - Dean's Council Minutes, 1970 (Box 8)
      - Future Projects-Beck (Box 8)
      - Faculty Minutes, 1978 (Box 8)
      - Faculty Minutes, 1969-1972 (Box 8)
      - Budget for Hotel School, 1922-1933 (Box 8)
      - Dean's Council, 1968-1970 (Box 9)
      - Education Committee Report, 1944 (Box 9)
      - Staff Meetings, 1976-1978 (Box 9)
      - Faculty Meetings, 1972-1976 (Box 9)
      - Petit. Meetings, 1975-1981 (Box 9)
      - Faculty Minutes, 1935-1959 (Box 9)
      - Cornell Faculty Salaries Analysis (Box 9)
      - Dean's Conferences, 1963-1967 (Box 10)